Guide to the Anna Halprin Papers, 1957-1995
American Dance Festival Archives
Anna Halprin papers 1957-1995
American Dance Festival Archives Box 90772 Durham, North Carolina, 27708-0772 USA Phone: 919-684-6402 Fax: 919-684-5459 Email: adfarchives@americandancefestival.org
Halprin, Anna.
1.33 linear feet Extent: 2 boxes
Anna Halprin (b. 1920) is a pioneering dancer and choreographer of the post-modern dance movement. She founded the San Francisco Dancer's Workshop in 1955 as a center for movement training, artistic experimentation, and public participatory events open to the local community. Halprin has created 150 full-length dance theater works and is the recipient of numerous awards including the 1997 Samuel H. Scripps Award for Lifetime Achievement in Modern Dance from the American Dance Festival. Her students include Meredith Monk, Trisha Brown, Yvonne Rainer, Simone Forti, Ruth Emmerson, Sally Gross, and many others. Collection includes books, magazines, photographic prints, clippings, flyers, written correspondence, programs, essays, and other printed materials.
RL.00021
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Patrons must sign the Acknowledgement of Legal Responsibility and Privacy Rights form before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Acquisitions Information
The Anna Halprin Papers were received by the American Dance Festival as a gift.
Biographical Note
Anna Halprin (b. 1920) is a pioneering dancer and choreographer of the post-modern dance movement. She enrolled in the University of Wisconsin in the late 1930s where she studied with Margaret D'Houbler and developed a strong interest in collaboration and improvisation in response to more formalized modern dance techniques. Over her long career, Halprin has stretched the perceived boundaries of dance to include theater, visual art, myth, ritual, and individual and collective healing. She founded the San Francisco Dancer's Workshop in 1955 as a center for movement training, artistic experimentation, and public participatory events open to the local community. Large-scale public pieces such as Circle the Earth and Myths demonstrated the development of Halprin's unique expressive and transformative arts technique. Halprin's own battle with cancer has deepened her interest in dance as a tool for transforming the suffering of age, illness, and death. In 1978 she co-founded the Tamalpa Institue with her daughter Daria as a research and educational non-profit in the field of movement-based healing arts. Halprin has created 150 full-length dance theater works and is the recipient of numerous awards including the 1997 Samuel H. Scripps Award for Lifetime Achievement in Modern Dance from the American Dance Festival. She is the co-creator of the RSVP Cycle, a creative methodology that can be applied to many disciplines beyond dance. Her students include Meredith Monk, Trisha Brown, Yvonne Rainer, Simone Forti, Ruth Emmerson, Sally Gross, and many others.
Collection Overview
Collection includes books, magazines, photographic prints, clippings, flyers, written correspondence, programs, essays, and other printed materials.
Collection Arrangement
The Anna Halprin Papers are organized into three series: Publications, Festival Programs, and Subject Files.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Halprin, Anna; San Francisco Dancers’ Workshop; Choreographers -- United States; Modern Dance -- United States
Contents of Collection
- Publications, 1957-1995 and undated, 17 Folders
  - Publications by Anna Halprin, 1975-1995 and undated
    - Dancers' Workshop (Box OS1)
    - Movement Ritual I, 1975
    - Citydance: Anna Halprin & San Francisco Dancers' Workshop 1977 (Box 1)
    - Discovering Dance, Lomi School Bulletin, Summer 1981
    - Circle the Earth Manual, 1987
    - Movement Ritual, 1990
    - Moving Toward Life: Five Decades of Transformational Dance, 1995 (hardcover)
    - Moving Toward Life: Five Decades of Transformational Dance, 1995 (softcover)
    - Dance as a Healing Art: A Teacher's Guide & Support Manual for People with Cancer, 1997
  - Publications about Anna Halprin, 1957-1963
    - Close-Up of Modern Dance Today: The Private Teacher, Dance Magazine, December 1957
    - Anna Halprin, Fresnans to Dance, California Crossroads, May 1960
    - I Balletti di Ann Helprin, Sipario, 1963
    - Manifold Applications, by Jack Anderson, Dance Magazine, April 1963 (2 copies)
    - La Nueva Coreografia Americana, by Giordano Falzoni, Mondo Occidentale, 1963
  - Publications collected by Anna Halprin, 1966-1988
    - Impulse: Current Trends, 1966
    - Something That's Happening: A Portrait of the Sausalito School District, 1968
    - Human Potential, Winter 1987/1988
- Festival Programs, 1963-1965, 6 Folders
  - Muzicki Biennale Zagreb, 1963 (2 copies) (Box 1)
  - La Biennale de Venezia Music Festival, 1963
  - Teatro Delle Arti, 1963
  - UCLA Concerts, Improvisation Festival, 1964
  - Muzicki Biennale Zagreb Bulletin, 1965 (2 copies)
  - Stockholms Festspel, 1965 (book and 2 copies bulletin)
- Subject Files, 1963-1985 and undated, 32 Folders
  - Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - Anna Halprin at ADF
  - Healing Arts
  - Dancer's Workshop Draft, Christmas 1973
  - Reviews from Early Years
  - Tamalpa Institute
  - Education, 1967 and undated
    - Writings, 1967
    - Movement Ritual
  - Performances and Community Events, 1963-1985 and undated
    - Kadosh
    - American Dance Season, ANTA Theater, 1955
    - Apartment 6, 1963
    - Five-Legged Stool, 1964
    - Birds of America, 1964
    - Parades and Changes
    - Myths, 1970
    - Hunter College Performance, 1970
    - Male-Female Rituals, 1974
    - Trace Dance, 1977
    - Search for Living Myths and Rituals, 1981
    - In the Mountain, On the Mountain, 1981-1985
    - Citydance
    - Experiments in the Environment Workshop (Box OS1)
    - Circle the Earth, 1985-1991 and undated
      - Flyers and Programs (Box 1)
      - Writings and Reviews
  - San Francisco Dancers' Workshop, 1965-1979 and undated
    - Annual Reports 1965-1967
    - Documentation Summer 1974
    - Documentation Winter 1975
    - Information Packet, 1976
    - Reach out Program Documentation, 1979
    - Philosophy
    - Publicity
    - Performances